## Matthew Guzdial Ph.D. Candidate, Georgia Institute of Technology

CONTACT INFORMATION College of Computing Lab: TSRB 228
Georgia Institute of Technology Cell: 404-683-9241

Atlanta, Georgia E-Mail: mguzdial3@gatech.edu
United States of America 30332 Web: http://www.guzdial.com/

#### RESEARCH AREAS

My research focuses on creative artificial intelligence and machine learning, with two major research vectors. The first is the application of AI/ML to domains we would typically consider requiring human creativity, which exposes limitations and potential for development of current AI/ML approaches. The second is the application of computational models of creativity to standard AI/ML tasks to improve the performance on these tasks.

#### **EDUCATION**

## **Georgia Institute of Technology**

Ph.D. in Computer Science

2019

Dissertation: "Combinational Machine Learning Creativity"

Ph.D. Committee: Mark Riedl (chair), Ashok Goel, Charles Isbell, Brian Magerko, Michael Mateas, and Devi Parikh

B.S. Computational Media with Honors Certificate in Social Psychology

2014

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Journals**

1. Procedural Content Generation via Machine Learning (PCGML). Adam Summerville, Sam Snodgrass, Matthew Guzdial, Christoffer Holmgård, Amy K. Hoover, Aaron Isaksen, Andy Nealen, and Julian Togelius, IEEE Transactions on Games, pp. 257–270, 2018.

## Conferences

- Player Experience Extraction from Gameplay Video. Zijin Lou, Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, Artificial Intelligence and Interactive Digital Entertainment (AIIDE), 2018.
- 3. Automated Game Design via Conceptual Expansion. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, Artificial Intelligence and Interactive Digital Entertainment (AIIDE), 2018.
- 4. Creative Invention Benchmark. Matthew Guzdial, Nicholas Liao, Vishwa Shah, and Mark Riedl, International Conference on Computational Creativity (ICCC), 2018.
- 5. Game Engine Learning from Video. Matthew Guzdial, Boyang Li, and Mark Riedl, International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), Acceptance Rate: 26%, 2017.
- 6. Evaluating Singleplayer and Multiplayer in Human Computation Games. Kristin Siu, Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, International Conference on the Foundations of Digital Games (FDG), 2017.
- 7. Game Level Generation from Gameplay Video. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, Artificial Intelligence and Interactive Digital Entertainment (AIIDE), 2016.
- 8. Learning to Blend Computer Game Levels. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, International Conference on Computational Creativity (ICCC), Best Paper Award, 2016.
- 9. Crowdsourcing Open Interactive Narrative. Matthew Guzdial, Brent Harrison, Boyang Li, and Mark Riedl, International Conference on the Foundations of Digital Games (FDG), 2015.

### **Short Papers**

10. Deep Convolutional Player Modeling on Log and Level Data. Nicholas Liao, Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, International Conference on the Foundations of Digital Games (FDG), 2017.

#### **Workshop Papers**

- 11. Co-Creative Level Design via Machine Learning. Matthew Guzdial, Nicholas Liao, and Mark Riedl, AIIDE Workshop on Experimental AI in Games (EXAG), 2018.
- 12. Towards Automated Let's Play Commentary. Matthew Guzdial, Shukan Shah, and Mark Riedl, AIIDE Workshop on Experimental AI in Games (EXAG), 2018.
- 13. Explainable PCGML via Game Design Patterns. Matthew Guzdial, Joshua Reno, Jonathan Chen, Gillian Smith, and Mark Riedl, AIIDE Workshop on Experimental AI in Games (EXAG), 2018.
- 14. Combinatorial Creativity for Procedural Content Generation via Machine Learning. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, AAAI Workshop on Knowledge Extraction from Games (KEG), 2018.
- 15. Combinatorial Meta Search. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, NIPS Workshop on Machine Learning Creativity and Design (MLCD), 2017.
- Visual Procedural Content Generation with an Artificial Abstract Artist. Matthew Guzdial, Duri Long, Christopher Cassion, and Abhishek Das, ICCC Workshop on Computational Creativity in Games (CCG), 2017.
- 17. Learning Player Tailored Content from Observation: Platformer Level Generation from Video Traces using LSTMs. Adam Summerville, Matthew Guzdial, Michael Mateas, and Mark Riedl, AIIDE Workshop on Experimental AI in Games (EXAG), 2017.
- 18. Deep Static and Dynamic Level Analysis: A Study on Infinite Mario. Matthew Guzdial, Nathan Sturtevant and Boyang Li, AIIDE Workshop on Experimental AI in Games (EXAG), 2016.
- 19. Toward Game Level Generation from Gameplay Videos. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, FDG Workshop on Procedural Content Generation in Games (PCG), 2015.

#### **Peer Reviewed Demos**

- 20. A General Level Design Editor for Co-creative Level Design. Matthew Guzdial, Jonathan Chen, Shao-Yu Chen, and Mark Riedl, Experimental Al in Games Workshop (EXAG), 2017.
- 21. Conceptually Blended Levels in a Unity Engine. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, Artificial Intelligence and Interactive Digital Entertainment (AIIDE), 2015.
- 22. An Intelligent Game Level Design Editor Informed by Gameplay Videos. Matthew Guzdial, and Mark Riedl, Experimental AI in Games Workshop (EXAG), 2015.

## Other

- 23. Explainable AI for Designers. Jichen Zhu, Rafael Bidarra, Alex J. Champandard, Simon Colton, Reynald Francois, Matthew Guzdial, Amy K. Hoover, Antonios Liapis, Sebastian Risi, Gillian Smith, Anne Sullivan, and G Michael Youngblood, Dagstuhl Seminar 1747: Artificial and Computational Intelligence in Games: AI-Driven Game Design, 2018.
- 24. Al As Reflective Practice. Gillian Smith, Mirjam P. Eladhari, Matthew Guzdial, Emily Short, Adam M. Smith, Anne Sullivan, Tommy Thompson, and R Michael Young, Dagstuhl Seminar 1747: Artificial and Computational Intelligence in Games: Al-Driven Game Design, 2018.
- 25. Al-assisted Board Game Play. Antonios Liapis, Michael Cook, Steve Dahlskog, Mirjam P. Eladhari, Matthew Guzdial, Emily Short, Gillian Smith, Anne Sullivan, and Tommy Thompson, Dagstuhl Seminar 1747: Artificial and Computational Intelligence in Games: Al-Driven Game Design, 2018.
- 26. What is Machine Learning/Deep Learning. Matthew Guzdial, Joshua A. McCoy, and Jichen Zhu, Dagstuhl Seminar 1747: Artificial and Computational Intelligence in Games: Al-Driven Game Design, 2018.

INVITED TALKS AND PANELS	University of Southern California Invited Talk: "Automated Game Genera	ation via Machine Learning"	2018
	Unite Los Angeles: Unity Developer Co Invited Talk: "Using Machine Learning to		<b>2018</b> kflows"
	Blizzard Invited talk: "Procedural Content General	ration via Machine Learning"	2017
	Foundations of Digital Games Panel: "Machine Learning for Procedur	al Content Generation"	2017
CONFERENCE / WORKSHOP ORGANIZATION	AAAI Workshop on Knowledge Extracti AAAI Workshop on Knowledge Extracti FDG Workshop on Procedural Content ICCC Media Chair ICCC Workshop on Computational Cre AIIDE Workshop on Experimental AI in	ion from Games Chair Generation Local Coordinator eativity Chair	2019 2018 2017 2017 2017 2016
Honors and Awards	Foley Scholar Finalist Heidelberg Laureate Forum Young Res Unity Graduate Fellowship Dagstuhl Seminar 1747 Participant Foley Scholar Finalist Best Paper Award, ICCC Conference National Science Foundation Graduate Georgia Tech College of Computing Be Georgia Tech President's Undergradua	Student Fellowship Honorable Men est Undergraduate Research Award	2018 2018 2018 2017 2017 2016 tion 2015 2013 2013
SELECT REVIEWING AND PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBERSHIP	Journal of Parallel and Distributed Com IEEE Transactions on Games (TOG), 2 IEEE Transactions on Computational Ir and Al-assisted Game Design, 2017. International Joint Conference on Artific ACM CHI Conference on Human Factor ACM Chi Conference on Designing Intelested Conference on Computational International Conference on the Found International Conference on Computational AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligent AIIDE Experimental AI in Games Work FDG Workshop on Procedural Content IndieCade, Juror Committee, 2014-201	ntelligence and AI in Games (TCIAIG cial Intelligence (IJCAI), 2018. ors in Computing Systems (CHI), 2019 eractive Systems (DIS), 2018. delligence and Games (CIG), 2018. ations of Digital Games (FDG), 2017 onal Creativity (ICCC), 2017-2018. ore and Interactive Digital Entertainn shop (EXAG), 2016-2018.	7-2018.
Teaching	Georgia Institute of Technology Term Spring 2018 Summor 2017	Course  Machine Learning	2014-present Instructor Effectiveness 4.82 / 5.0

3

Game Al

4.95 / 5.0

2014-present

Summer 2017

**Georgia Institute of Technology** 

Co-designed new Game Al course, two-time Primary Instructor, and Teaching Assistant

## Georgia Institute of Technology

2010-2014

2017

2016

Teaching Assistant: Game AI

#### STUDENTS Current

Yalini Kumar (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2018-present
Andrew Hoyt (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2018-present
Kenny Scharm (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2018-present
Maxwell Bronstein (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2018-present
Joshua Reno (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2018-present
Zijin Lou* (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2017-present
Shukan Shah* (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2017-present
Vishwa Shah* (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2017-present
Jonathan Chen (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology	2016-present

#### Graduated

Nicholas Liao\* (CS Undergrad), Georgia Institute of Technology "Deep Convolutional Player Modeling on Log and Level Data"

Shao-Yu Chen (CS Masters), Georgia Institute of Technology

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Disney Research, Pittsburgh, PA - Research Assistant Intern Applied deep learning to player experience prediction and simulation. May 2016- August 2016

Zynga Inc., Orlando FL - Design Intern

Led weekly bug-fix count across entire team of twenty-six developers.

May 2014 - August 2014

Zynga Inc., San Francisco, CA - Production Intern

May 2013 - August 2013

Developed mobile game prototype single-handedly then lead small team in further development.

## **PRESS**

"Al makes new video games by watching people play Super Mario and Kirby' New Scientist, October 2018. link

"Video Games Created Using Artificial Intelligence" BBC, September 2018. link

"Forget dumping games designers for AI turns out it takes two to tango" The Register, September 2018. link

"This Video Game Made by Al Looks Fun as Hell" Motherboard, September 2018. link

"An A.I. is designing retro video games and they're surprisingly good" Digital Trends, September 2018. link

"Al learns to re-create Super Mario Bros by watching someone else play it" The Verge, September 2017. link

"Artificial Intelligence is Learning To Develop Games" Rolling Stone, September 2017. link

<sup>\*</sup>indicates winner of PURA, a prestigious undergraduate research award at the Georgia Institute of Technology

"Al System Accurately Replicates Video Games Just by Watching Them" The Seeker, September 2017.

"New AI can 'clone' the basic software that brings a video game to life after watching the original for just TWO MINUTES" Daily Mail, September 2017. link

"Has a Black Mirror episode predicted the future of video games?" The Guardian, October 2016. link

"Underwater Castle? This Al Creates Never-Before-Seen 'Super Mario Bros.' Level" Motherboard, March 2016. link

"How Computers Learned to Play Mario" Smithsonian Magazine, November 2015. link

"Algorithm Turns Fiction into Interactive Games" Popular Science, September 2015. link

"This AI Creates Interactive Fiction by Reading Other People's Stories" Motherboard, September 2015. link

"This Al Builds Super Mario Levels by Watching YouTube" WIRED, June 2015. link

#### REFERENCES

Mark Riedl (PhD Supervisor), Georgia Institute of Technology, riedl@cc.gatech.edu Charles Isbell, Georgia Institute of Technology, isbell@cc.gatech.edu Nathan Sturtevant, University of Alberta, nathanst@ualberta.ca Jessica Hodgins, Carnegie Mellon University, jkh@cs.cmu.edu Michael Mateas, University of California, Santa Cruz, michaelm@soe.ucsc.edu